welcome everyone to
our monthly q a uh first of all i want
to begin by
apologizing that we needed a uh to do
the time shift
uh normally we do the q a uh the
uh the third friday of the month uh 3
p.m eastern time
um we're in october here in canada
toronto
and we're going through a period where
the weather is highly variable
and when there's lots of rapid
barometric and humidity change
um it really messes up the mirrors in my
my in my left ear
um and i was not capable of i was on a
place where i could
do the q a last friday i apologize for
that things are a little bit better now
they're not perfect but
they're doable and a lot of a lot of
life
is not having things perfect but just
having them
doable so we're going to proceed now
as always we're going to start with uh
some questions from uh patrons
um and then towards the end we'll move
to questions from the live chat
so the first is from an anonymous patron
whoever you are thank you for your
support
the question is what are the best
practices for character development
um so i think the best practices for
character development is to see
character
as a uh base
a as a system of virtues uh
that you identify with and
and then and then also to see each
virtue as a particular way of being wise
um and so we go through these um
we can think about how do we cultivate a
virtue
uh we cultivate a virtue uh
by thinking about the ways
in which well this model comes from
aerosol the ways in which
uh we're trying to make our uh our
behavior as appropriate
uh to the situation where the situation
all often includes things that
are we regard is inherently valuable
because care
virtue has to do with our relationship
to what is true
what is good and what is beautiful um so
using a standard example from
aristotle um so my relationship
one way in which i have a relationship
to the truth and to goodness
sometimes even to beauty is my speech
and so one of the virtues uh let's say
zero in more on truth
um is you know uh being honest um
and so what do i want to do well i i can
i can go wrong in two ways
i can uh say too much too often
um and that would make me boorish
uh it would make me interruptive it
would uh it would
detract from other people's ability to
speak um
it could be unkind it could be
overwhelming
um it could be cruel um so i don't want
i don't want to just say everything that
i'm thinking
that's you know um but how could i i
could also fail to say enough
uh and uh i could be
in that sense i could be you know kind
of cowardly
i could be manipulative by being passive
aggressive i could be deceptive by being
inadequate uh in the amount of
information i'm presenting
or another example courage i if i face
danger too often i'm just an idiot
if i avoid it always i'm a coward
so what you have to do is you cultivate
virtues
and you you cultivate virtues by
basically setting up
habits that act as what's called a
virtual engine you set up habits
of noticing and counteracting
like reducing when you're
deviating by being by doing too much by
saying too much or facing too much
danger and then you also set up habits
that motivate you to get you to
to generate behavior when you're not
saying enough
or when you're not facing enough danger
and so you build up habits that act of
what's called a virtual engine
some of them are making you do more when
you've been doing too little
and some of you some of them are
limiting your behavior when you're doing
too much
so you you basically cultivate virtues
by
uh cultivating virtual engines but then
of course virtues don't stand
separately from each other right you
want to cultivate
virtues in relationship to each other
you need to get good at getting a
systematic relationship between
the virtues so like
am i when and and this is this is where
you know a lot of literature
um and parable and myth is very helpful
because what
parables often do one of my favorite is
the parable of the prodigal son
is it tells you how our various virtues
are in
a non-reducible non-resolvable tension
with each other the parrot or the the
prodigal son tells us
that compassion and uh and justice
are right if you always do pursue
compassion
uh that's not that that's not good if
you always pursue justice
at the expense of compassion that's not
good they have trade-off relationships
so you figure out
trade-off relationships between
the virtues so they get to come into a
systematic relationship now you're
starting to cultivate
character but there is another degree
of systematicity that you have to
address which is
you're cultivating that those trade-off
relationships between the virtues
also in how they complement your
personality
so character is often described as
second nature
because you're taking on all these
habits and then systems of habits
right you're doing all this virtual
engineering and then putting the virtues
together
in opponent processing of various
virtues
but you're doing all of that ultimately
to compensate
for your personality where personality
doesn't mean your personhood
personality means uh your your
dispositional traits
um you know and we often talk about the
big five or the big six
like are you more open or you are are
you less open are you more introverted
extroverted
and what you have to do is you have to
cultivate your your virtues and your
skills
uh to compensate for uh the deficits
in your personality and so that's a
process of identification
what virtues are you identifying with
and how do they fit together with your
constitutional
personality but running through all of
this is
that what you're throughout and this
helps you to coordinate
and and create the system of the virtues
is the idea that ever
that virtue as i like to say is the
beauty of wisdom
every virtue is a way of
seeing what is most appropriate in
a situation and acting appropriately
towards it
so every virtue requires this
the this linking of discerning what
discerning through appearances
discerning through self-deception
discerning through distortion seeing
right discerning the relationship
between the larger perspective of
various virtues what's happening here
now in this situation
and also being sensitive uh being
open to what's disclosing itself in the
situation so you're trying to get this
harmonic relationship between
discernment
and disclosure and what you're trying to
do
in in every situation in which you're
trying to act virtuously
is you're trying to like courage i'm
trying to see through the way in which
fear might be distorting and biasing my
vision
to see what's really being disclosed
here so that i can act most
appropriately to this situation
so then above and beyond the habits
coming into virtues
the virtues being systemized into
characters into character
you are engaging in a comprehensive
ecology of practices
for the cultivation of wisdom and i've
i've talked a lot about this both from a
scientific
uh perspective of the best sort of
science of what that looks like
and also from a practical existential
perspective
of teaching people uh uh
ecologies and practices from the eastern
wisdom traditions buddhism and taoism
and also right now from the western
wisdom traditions
um epicureanism stoicism and
neoplatonism we're about to move into
neoplatonism
so i think if you have that nested and
now going from top down wisdom
into the system of virtues and then the
virtues
into you know uh a a virtual engines of
habit
that are fitting to your personality in
a complementary
compensatory manner so you have deep
identification with your character
a deep interweaving of personality of
care and character this way
and then also of course personality in
with personhood
your moral agency then i think that's
how you can appropriately
uh cultivate uh uh your character
so uh the next is from testitos uh
patron thank you very much
uh uh for your support uh and this
second question overlaps with the first
um what are
sorry what are some technologies what
are some psychotechnologies
to organize self to future self
relationships
that possibly increase goal salience and
help chaining
uh daily congruent actions together
you've mentioned virtues and virtual
engines
which i've just done having needs versus
becoming needs
some others talk about goals versus
values companies use quarterly
objectives and key results
is there a good system to think about
these uh together
uh yes so i think there is and this is
where
i rely a lot on well first of all
uh everything that i just previously
said uh
goes into answering this about how you
nest psychotechnologies
for the virtual engineering of habit and
then uh
the the the systematization uh virtues
and then the identification interweaving
with personality in one side
and personhood and another and
overarching that um setting it within a
a a a trajectory and a tradition of
wisdom cultivation
that is all very important you also need
within it
you need uh behavior in which you
are engaging what uh agnes callard calls
aspiration
in which you are putting the future self
and the current self into dialogue meyer
seth and fishbach
and their work on self-regulation talk
about this as frame widening
it is a good practice to dialogue with
your future self well you say your
future self doesn't exist well let i'm
going to come back and refine that a
little bit
but think about the point about the
dialoguing of the future you dialogue
with your future self obviously this is
an imaginative visualization practice
but this is no different than the kind
of imagination
imagination visualization processes we
do in therapy
where we'll talk to different aspects of
ourselves and we use
imagery for do that or we do the empty
chair technique when we talk to
right uh uh perhaps uh somebody
obviously somebody who's not present
perhaps somebody i remember when i was
going through uh
a therapy therapy we did the view the
empty chair technique and i was talking
to my dead mother obviously
so this is a version of serious play
serious play is
needed in order to set up a dialogue
between yourself and future self because
you need
your while your current self causes your
future self
your future self normatively challenges
your current self and so they have a
biological relationship each is
is contributing and so you have to give
voice
you have to imaginatively invoke your
future self and give voice to your
future self
and allow it to talk you ways in which
you can implement that
are journaling um you can even have a
future self that's at the end of the day
so when so i know i'm going through my
day and i'm trying to note my biases for
active open-mindedness
i know that my journal waits for me and
my my journal is almost like this
this future self that's going to reflect
back on what's happening right now and
that's how they're talking to each other
you can actually do it directly through
imagination you can do it through syria
play practices
there are versions of active role
playing
uh that allow you to get into this
dialogue
of course if you belong to a religious
tradition there are religious traditions
uh that allow this kind of practice uh
to occur when you
you're talking to your soul or to your
character or to your better self
but there's also practices that you do
now um
that have to do with trying to
right here right now you can see this
even some therapies like dialectical
behavioral therapy where you try to give
voice to your wise self
because your wise self is the self that
is often
trying to speak on behalf of your future
self because
aspiration is ultimately a process of
what's called proleptic
rationality aspiration requires is bound
up enmeshed with
wisdom cultivation so you try and sense
your wise self
so i mean part of that is with your
journaling you can
try to note the ways throughout the day
in which you were virtuous
this is also called watering your buddha
in the buddhist tradition
you try and right it's one of the three
jewels the buddha the dharma the sangha
you try to remember throughout the day
when you were more like the buddha or
you're more like christ or you're more
like socrates
and you celebrate it and you you
identify with it you
you invoke it and you you you you
basically
affirm that you want that to grow within
you to
to to to become uh more prevalent within
you
and then what you can do is also and
this was a technique
uh that has been it's a perennial
technique it goes back to the stoics
jordan peterson has more recently
revived it
you do reverse journaling you you
write a reverse narrative you write
about your future
potential future selves and then you
write the narrative
like it's like you're reverse
engineering it okay here's john and
things have gone really horrible how did
he get there and you
write a reverse narrative and here's
john and things have gone very well in a
reverse narrative
and then you use that for discernment
and disclosure so you know how to move
forward
um so all of these when you practice
them at least i
found um they all mutually reinforce
they just naturally start to glum onto
each other
and mutually afford and reinforce each
other and so if you integrate what i've
just said with my previous answer
about the cultivation of character i
think that's a way of answering your
question
at least i hope it's helpful i'm here uh
the next question is from
rachel hayden who's also a patron
hello john thank you so much for the
book list advice last month you're
welcome rachel
rachel uh so far i've really enjoyed on
in particular
as you should it is rightly considered a
masterpiece uh
and for those of you who are unaware of
it it's the classic work by harry frank
for
distinguishing bullshitting i'm not
trying to be of all gear this is a term
it's it's being used technically
bullshitting from lying
so basically the idea is the liar
manipulates you by because of the way
you care about the truth
and telling you pretending that
something that isn't true
is true the artist tries to
manipulate you by getting you to not
care
whether or not something is true or not
and just be caught up in how salient
it is um some people have
uh i just want to slow down a little bit
about this
um the idea is
we are often self-deceptive this is a
socratic idea
when we find things salient beyond our
understanding
of them we so we're not really we're not
we're
our concern for the truth or the at
least the understanding
of what we're after is not calibrated
is not coordinated with how salient and
motivating something is
so you can often ask people why you're
doing this well i really want this
um and then you ask them well do you
actually understand the phenomena that
you want do you understand
what it entails like well i want to be
happy okay
what's happiness what well you're
pursuing it so deeply what
is it what is it how do you understand
it very well
so the idea is we can often
ourselves because
the where the salience of things
is so radically disconnected uh from our
understanding now some people say
but sometimes like especially in therapy
or other situations
the salience is there way before the
understanding that's why i'm in therapy
um i think that's a very good point but
i would say
that's to that's that means you haven't
fully picked up on
that intention defies action what's the
difference between a wink and a blink
well
it's the intention behind the action
when
you're in a situation in which somebody
is making something salient
at the expense of understanding its
truth
because they don't want you to question
them anymore
they don't want you to reflect and
explore that's bullshitting
when the salience exceeds our
understanding and that is
motivating us to increase our
understanding to ask questions and
explore like we do in therapy
that of course is wonder and socrates
famously said that
uh wisdom begins in wonder so if once we
distinguish
those two together we can understand we
have these two aspects
to bullshitting which is the right the
separation of salience from
understanding or for
caring about the truth and that goes to
and that is directly framed in order to
try and shut down
questioning shut down wondering shut
down reflection
shut down the attempt to to cultivate
wisdom
okay so all of that is now i think a
good enough background
so i want to now go on with rachel's
question
as a uf citizen oh boy i'm a canadian
and like the rest of the world we're
watching what's happening in the united
states with
um an increasing mixture of concern
and fascination and fear
um especially for canadians because
you know we share this long border and
we're a very small country
uh population wise compared to the
united states and militarily
so it's a very concerning thing so i
understand your situation i have lots of
friends
in the united states rachel and the
degree
of
anxiety that they're expressing um is
really significant
so as a u.s citizen how does one work at
the meta-political level while not
abdicating responsibility at the
political level
so i'll i'll finish up the rest of the
question a sec
the distinction uh the political level
is the political level
uh is where you identify for a
particular position
uh which advocates a set of policies
that are supposed to bring about a
particular goal
and that's that's the political level um
the metapolitical level
is uh working at the level of what
are the cultural cognitive processes
that are presupposed by that previous
level
what what do we need to do in order to
be able to have
a system that is self-correcting so that
we can select the correct policies and
the correct goals and the correct ways
of implementing the policies
so in particular i'm very concerned and
i've had some discussions with zach
stein about this um also with brent
cooper
about uh that the metapolitical level
has
uh very significantly degraded the
united states
uh we that we have lost the commitment
uh to the idea that we are largely
self-deceptive
and we need people who are opposing us
in order to give us the opponent
processing that is self-corrective
like you find in all biological systems
instead we have turned that into
adversarial processing
in which the chances that i'm wrong are
minimal
i'm right i'm self-righteously right
both sides say this
um the left to say i'm self-righteously
right in getting you
and pointing out you know how much human
beings are subject to fate
and the and the right says i'm
self-righteously right and telling you
how much we should hold human beings
individually responsible for their
behavior
and of course like the prodigal son and
then like justice and compassion
they're both right and they're both
wrong and at different times and at
different degrees
and we need them to cooperate at not at
the political level
at the metapolitical level of being
committed
to the process over their position so
that ultimately
everybody everybody benefits from the
self-correction
so the problem is how do you work at the
how do you those two levels right now
especially united states are like
there's a dichotomy or even an
antagonism between them
because people are so identified
self righteously with their position
often
and an adversarial processing that
it's very difficult to get people to
consider
the the fact that we should be
ultimately committed to democracy to
rationality and democracy above and
beyond
our particular goals and position the
fact that most americans
are more afraid and are more distrustful
of the opposing party republicans of
democrats and democrats of republican
than they are of foreign enemies tells
you that the country is in a
very bad place indeed so how do you work
at that
level how do you how do you put those
two together when the
political and the meta-political level
are so antagonistically
poised with respect to each other so i i
want to read the rest of rachel's
question there is such a myriad of
pressing political issues
but with the metacrisis unfolding so
rapidly it also
almost seems counterproductive to spend
so much energy on as you say increasing
unhelpful left-right debates
yes and so the connection i take it that
rachel's making is
with adversarial processing with winner
take
all zero-sum gain and the other side
is distrustful and evil uh the
you see the dialogue moving more and
more towards bullshitting
on on all on all sides um
and it's interesting that if you take a
look at work at sloman and you get
people and they come into these
situations and they're
so opposed to each other and you
you get them to talk about their values
in the position it just exacerbates it
but let's say that that uh let's say
it's about health care
what a big issue in the united states if
you if you if you shift and say well
before we get to the positions and the
values
can you guys both explain what what is
health care
how it functions how it actually works
and
why it's breaking down and why it's not
fun like what's the actual machinery of
healthcare
what happens is and this is what's
called the knowledge illusion
this is a way in which we systematically
ourselves
we confuse the salience of our
access to information with the depth of
our understanding
you can see this in even very mundane
things do you know how a bicycle works
oh yeah
sure sure i understand bicycle draw a
bicycle draw bicycle a diagram
that will actually explain to me how it
works most people can't do it do you
know how the toilet works oh yeah sure
sure well draw a diagram show me how
does it work
um oh i don't know
so we we suffer from the knowledge
illusion and notice this weird feedback
loop the knowledge illusion
makes us ourselves and focus
on our values and our positions which
then exacerbate the knowledge of
illusion and make the adversarial
processing worse but in the experiments
what happened is
when you ask people to explain the
mechanism
of the phenomena over which they're
disagreeing
if they're honest and people aren't
always honest but if people are just
dishonest
there's not a lot we can do but if
they're honest and in the experiments
they are
what happens is you see them converging
towards each other
they start genuine dialogue because
the realization of their shared
ignorance causes the realization of
shared humility
and the shared need for wondering and
for becoming
wiser for getting a coordination between
discernment and disclosure going on
and that's how you can do it so i would
recommend to you
that what what you can do is you can do
this within these situations
you can try and get people that are left
right to
right still do deal with a political
issue and then okay we need to solve
this problem
but instead of values in the position
let's work on getting a very clear
explanation
of what the phenomenon actually is
for you personally um rachel
i don't know if i'm the best person to
ask for this advice
uh so that's a general uh and i mean a
piece of advice that i just gave you i
hope you find that helpful
but personally uh this is um i've become
increasingly frustrated
uh and and i see friends and family
being being bludgeoned into silence
from both the left and the right up
both the left and the right um
undermining
science and doing engaging in
revisionist history
that it supports their particular i
political ideology
um and when that's happening
um it it's hard to be virtuously allied
uh with either the left or the right
um and it's happening um
i i consider myself uh quite
quite left for uh for most of
my my history but i increasingly think
that's
irrelevant uh because the left and the
right to my mind are now
undermining right are mutually
undermining through the tsunami of
uh the metapolitical level um this
uh the uh science and history
um and and those three are so
interconnected together by the way
they all mutually depend on each other
uh that it's very hard
so i suppose my response
there then and what i've sort of
defaulted to is while working as much as
i can
to get people to converge and to also
afford
a a re-identification with the
metapolitical level and a recommitment
to it
at the political level i recommend to
people um
trying to find people uh at this third
and this isn't a trivial thing about to
say but i generally are looking for
people who just
who display uh virtue and wisdom
and that for me takes priority so i've
in canada i've watched
um the canadian governments
handle the covet crisis and this is just
an objective fact just look
at the numbers okay i don't want to
argue with anything about this
we're handling the covet crisis way
better the united states
and i've seen this uh that you know
a quite leftist liberal government
because it's
a de facto coalition between a liberal
gov a liberal government
and a socialist party or socialist
parties actually
a very right work cooperatively with a
with a quite
uh right of center provincial government
that's working with
a right center municipal government and
everybody acted pragmatically and
virtuously
and they practice listening to the
science and discernment
and then pain being sensitive to what
was being disclosed
and so all three of these levels have my
support
because they're saving lives
and they're putting aside their
positions and their ideologies
in order to save lives and so to what
degree you can find that happening
um in the people you want at the
political level to support
i recommend that's what you do but also
look for people
at the political level who care about
really who
care about it with their character care
about
the meta-political level and care about
the interconnections between the
political level
and science and history dewey made a
brilliant argument
john dewey the great pragmatist
philosopher that democracy science
and history practice well mutually
depend and afford each other
and anything that is pulling them apart
and fraying them
and making them subservient to the
victory of an ideological
position will always have i hope
my virtuous resistance so thank you very
much rachel for your question
and i hope i didn't get a little over
dramatic there um i care about what's
going on
because literally hundreds of thousands
of people are dying
and then literally millions of lives are
being disrupted
and destroyed and covid is making the
meeting crisis worse
and so her question your question rachel
deserved an in-depth answer
the next question is from a patron a
friend of mine i get to talk to him
regularly
um once a month he's also uh
been i also met him uh uh personally
before
any of this uh before this
meaning my online presence uh sort of
expanded the way it has
um he's helped me he was involved
with the uh demonstration of the
philosophical friendship
so i'm talking about robert gray um and
it's always a pleasure
uh to interact with robert so robert's
question is what is lost from online
teaching compared to in-person teaching
perhaps at the high school college age
level what is gain
if you had the resources is there any
cool idea you implement using modern
technology
to take to change the way mass education
works today
thanks john nmr i hope you are both warm
actually
uh rob it's actually it's warm right now
uh in toronto uh it's we're getting a
freakish day
for late october in toronto it's it's
supposed to get up to 23 but it's
it's like a spring day here which of
course is going to confuse
everybody uh everybody's uh
circadian rhythms and stuff like that
it's also not
particularly good with my ear in fact i
can starting to feel it coming on my ear
but anyways it's a great question let me
do it the other way around
rob because i was surprised about what
i've noticed what by what's gained by
the online teaching
uh so what i use in my online teaching
is i used a a flipped classroom model
what that means is i record so i record
my lectures
asynchronously and they're put online
and the students can watch them whenever
they want to and that helps to deal with
you know that that's nice because it
bridges between
you know having live action speech and
having you know written text
they can watch it at different times
they can re-watch it uh they're not
bound by
time zones and then what i have is
time in the week that would normally be
dedicated to the lecture
i have what i call town halls and so
what i do is i break that time up let's
say it's a three hour block
into half hour increments and then i
break the class up into small
cohorts of around 10 people or so or if
it's a larger class
you know more but still much smaller and
then what people come in
on zoom in in the zoom room and we have
open discussion which they're
they're they're coming they've watched
the lecture and they're instructed to
come in with
making connections comments
criticisms asking for clarifications
bringing up topics for discussion
and what this me what this has me what
i've do what i've gained
is two things i get to have more
one-on-one
interaction with my students and i get
to know them more personally which helps
me
tailor my education to them and tailor
my
feedback to them and also what's
enhanced is student-to-student
interaction students are much more
likely to talk to each other
and also feel supported which was odd
because it's a virtual environment so
that was definitely gained
what was lost and this is strange
what's lost in this is really important
and it's something i'm struggling to
figure out how to do and i'm struggling
to figure out because i'm not only a
teacher i'm the director of the cogside
program
at the university of toronto what's lost
is the hallway experience
we can capture right now pretty good i
think i just described it
what what was going on in the classroom
but what we don't have
right is the hallway experience which is
especially important at college level
right but also to some degree at the
high school level
this is when people are outside the
classroom in the hallways we're also
lacking this at conferences
the foyer experience we're doing the
rooms we're listening to the speakers
but we're not actually you know
conferring
we're not meeting together in the
hallways or the foyers
and talking to each other and doing that
weird blending
of fixing the personal and the
professional
right meaning your education right or
your professional practice
together in discourse where we we move
with humor
and right between you know sociality
and epistemology and all of that
is so vital so
deeply vital it's like the hallways are
the arteries and the veins along which
you know education flows and the the
rooms are the organs
and those organs are now starved for the
circulation
that makes them so vital vitally alive
and so what's been lost is the hallway
experience
but trying a lot of things and the
technology is
it's it allows me to do some of that um
some of it a bit here and there but the
technology's not good enough
having what i would want is a technology
that
implemented the hall rooms and the
foyers
in between the classes um and of course
there's a bit of this going on with the
discord server
but then the coordination there isn't an
overarching coordination
technology yet between them um and so
what's happening is
like with ammar's amazing techno mage
help trying to loop together you know
youtube and zoom and discord and other
things
um and it depends on his particular
genius
uh to be uh functional but
i what i would really like is a
technology that made that really smooth
and powerful
and very userly user intuitive friendly
because i'm something of a techno
peasant when it comes to that level of
stuff
and then i would like and this goes to
the conversations i've had with jordan
hall and with zach stein
i would like a the development
of the cultural cognitive grammar of
deal of dialectic into the logos that
optimizes us for dwelling in and
coordinating those two spaces together
the circulatory system of the hallway
and the vital organs
of the classrooms so i hope that answers
your question
well it's a really good question and
really important
next question uh this is from an
anonymous patron
and i want to thank you for your support
um how do i forgive myself for my
mistakes
that's a question uh that i deeply
identify with
um some degree i think because of my
personal
personality i'm socially phobic by
nature
uh quite introverted
and then also because of my upbringing i
was brought up in a very punitive form
of fundamentalist christianity
um i i have internalized um
a very sadistic superego as my very good
friend
leo ferraro designates it um
and so this is a question that i've
wrestled with very significantly
um it it it um it
it it puts pressure it tends to fragment
or at least threat uh you know sheer
make threadbare uh the fabric the
tapestry
of my sense of self because uh when i
look back at my previous self
it it i tend to i tend to want to pull
away
uh because of uh the foolishness
and the vice that i see in my past self
and i mean and this is not i hope it is
i mean it doesn't i'm doing it right now
uh i i hope this is this is genuine and
not just false modesty
right or egocentrism so i pull away and
then
that takes the fragment um
that's one well that's one of the
reasons why uh the the the prospect of
personal immortality i find horrific
uh because that fraying um
strikes me as would just be inseparable
cleavage and destruction given enough
time
so i'm sorry that was a long preamble to
tell you how seriously i take this
question
so i have found uh there's a
there's practices from the eastern
tradition and the western traditions
that help me to deal with that and
what they do is they help me to
replace punitive guilt
with two things replace punitive guilt
with moral guilt
and replace punishment part of
right that's that's part of punitive
guilt with what's called intelligent
regret
so uh punitive psychological guilt is
basically what you're doing is you're
hurting yourself psychologically
you are paining yourself as a way of
trying to modify your behavior
now all behavior modification starts
there pedagogically
but that the mistake is to end there if
you were to
like if you were to just use punishment
on a dog
all the time you're going to turn it
into a monster
right in fact you want to you want to
use
as little this is what all the research
shows even with your kids
right so think about it with yourself
you want to use as little punishment
that is necessary
for bringing about compliance often we
we have trained ourselves sadistic super
ego
to over punish way beyond
what is needed for modifying our
behavior
so we have to let that go we have to let
that go so what do we do
well what we do is we first try to put
aside
psychological guilt and look at moral
guilt part of what i do in the
journaling is every day
i get into the habit
habit tends to reduce the overdramatic
nature that our consciousness
always brings with us part of what
consciousness does is it just
turns up the drama on everything
so you get into the habit of
acknowledging you know writing when
when what was a what was a vice that i
committed today
i was dishonest uh a vice of commission
what was
you know i was dishonest what what was
uh what was a vice of omission i could
have been more empathetic there
but you get it into the habit of doing
it now what happens is
all of the super affect starts to go
away because you're more
interested in the virtue of this you're
more interested in cultivating the
virtue i also look for my bias
my particular like about so you know i
caught myself today oh the narrative
bias there it is again
that's literally happened right and so
you
you you you get this middle place
between ah
and ignoring it because you're noting it
down you're writing it down in the third
person
and then i do the fourth thing i also
try to notice
a virtue a way in which again my inner
buddha expressed itself or my inner
socrates
came to life and i don't get all i do
that
i don't do that from like oh look how
great i am i try to
you know hold against narcissism but
genuinely
right because if you are genuinely being
attracted to the virtue
eventually you'll get softer sun you'll
get that meta virtue you'll you don't
you won't have to resist the temptation
to the vice
because you've gotten into the habit of
finding the virtue so salient
just like as an adult you don't find
your children's toys or children
programming
so tempting anymore you can get to the
place where you're more and more tempted
to the good
and then that goes along with replacing
punishment
with intelligent regret you get to the
place
where like if your friend has done
something
wrong you talk to them as a friend you
don't punish them
you don't make them feeling really bad
you might do that a little tiny bit
minimal force to get compliance to get
people to listen to you
and to take seriously and to commit to a
behavioral change that's what compliance
means
compliance doesn't mean subservience so
minimal force
but what mostly do you when you persuade
them
you persuade them you say well look
what's happening and look at how you're
getting trapped and look at how this is
self-deceptive and self-destructive
and you also inspire them to aspiration
look this is what i really
love about you you have this like you
try and train them in softer sun
in turning their eyes so they're tempted
to the good well do that to yourself
befriend yourself with intelligent
regret
replace psychological
guilt with moral guilt by getting into
the habit
of reflecting on your vices and your
virtues
so that it's not just this overwhelming
affective place because those habits
will actually modify your behavior much
better than all this punitive affect
especially if those habits are conjoined
to intelligent regret
which appeals to you as an intelligent
potentially
rational adult
rather than as a pre-linguistic
child so i hope that's helpful to you
as a way it's been very helpful to me
it's an ongoing project
i suspect i mean i suspect that i will
always be skewed
i see it in my behavior i see it but the
friends that i love
telling me uh that i still am skewed by
my sadistic super ego
but it is something that
i think i've the the advice i'm giving
you
i'm finding it helpful in my life in
making a difference
and giving me a life that is left
overshadowed
by this you know this
bronze age capricious
deity all right we are shifting to live
questions from the
chat and thank you again all the patreon
supporters and everyone watching us
right now as you know but i it always
should be said
your support is crucial to contributing
to producing
uh these videos the lecture series
and for supporting the science that
we're doing to find solutions to the
meeting crisis
and we are doing the science we're
starting to fund it we're starting to
get the experiments going
even in these difficult times uh so the
first question is from karima who's a
patron
it's great to have you here karima you
you you left
a comment on a video recently i think it
was the video in
uh in which i was doing invoking the
logos and your comment was much
appreciated thank you
what in your current research on
consciousness is news something that
astonishes
you uh wow
um that's that's a hard question um i'm
sorry
this this sounds like a hallmark card
from cognitive science but
consciousness never ceases to astonish
me it's it's that kind of phenomena
and i think if you're in a place where
consciousness ceases to astonish you
i think you don't you're not aware of
what consciousness is anymore uh
so but i don't mean to sound flippant uh
flip it
i mean i'm doing uh for those of you who
are interested this question i've been
helped
um with uh by my good friend and
colleague greg enriquez we're going
through a series
of dialogues of sort of a mixture of
lecture and dialogue
and trading back and forth between
myself and greg called untangling the
world not
which with developing an argument about
trying to give an account of
consciousness
um and the fact that
um what's astonishing me about
consciousness is
it
i mean but i'm trying to separate my
it's bound up with the answer i just
gave like
consciousness it
we've tended i i want to be very
respectful of my colleagues because
they're
right but we've tended to play make
consciousness
this separate weird thing and we don't
know what it does or how it emerges
and that's one way that's one way of
capturing
um how sort of unique a phenomena it is
and some people then tie sort of they
hang
they treat it as a spiritual skyhook in
which they try and hang
various very questionable metaphysics um
but the opposite is happening to me i'm
seeing how
interwoven because i'm also preparing a
course
on the called the elusive self on the
nature and function of self
so how interwoven consciousness is with
um intelligence and the self
and agency and biology
and consciousness
like so it's the op it's kind of the
opposite of it's this weird thing that
doesn't fit in
consciousness is kind of for me
ontological super glue right now
um and it glues to
it it contributes to the processes by
which the self is glued together
uh the agent is glued to the world
the different kinds of knowing
especially protect bacterial and
participatory
are are glued together um
the way our intelligence and relevance
realization
is is glued to you know
aspects of uh the way
our personalities
connect us to the world you know you
know intelligence is sort of
relevance realization within people
personality is basically
a way in which evolution has distributed
relevance realization across people
because we have these various different
degrees of openness
and conscientiousness and stuff we
actually get this amazing
um capacity to realize
relevance in distributed cognition and
so
all all consciousness is gluing all
those together and it's moving us all
around
uh and and it's it is tremendous
self-transformative capacity like in
mystical experience or in
uh when you get when you get when you're
in deal when you're in the uh like the
practicing dial dialectic and the deal
logos and you get that
that third factor the sense of the logos
the we space emerging
and that weird that weird and wonderful
consciousness associated with it
so for me what's astonishing right now
is the power and breadth and depth of
the super glue of consciousness
so here's another question uh from uh
jackson lipford who's also a patron
how does one dream and set goals for the
future allah reverse narratives without
inviting self-deception and bullshitting
um so the the the thing is uh
and this has been one of my concern
about
i don't know i don't know if peterson
does this
i i i've i haven't seen it i haven't
been privy enough to the inside of this
how it works so
i don't i'm not criticizing that but i
have seen people
implementing this uh the reverse
narratives falling prey to what
jackson is exactly saying self-deception
and
and and and then the answer there is
right um well do a lot to really
undermine the machinery
of uh by getting into the
practices
in which you're constantly trying to
deeply reintegrate
what you find salient with what you find
right
important uh sorry what that's that's
that was the equivalent way of
putting it integrating what you find
salient with your
your attempts to understand as deeply
what you take to be true or most real um
and so you have to be you there's
nothing in the practice i would say
of reverse narratives that's going to do
this job i think you have to be
cultivating
uh an ecology of practices that's about
cultivating wisdom and virtue
and you have to pay much more attention
much more attention
to how the world and other people
are telling you you are transforming
than from your own first-person
perspective
because of course we overestimate how
well we're doing
we over interpret our experiences
because of narcissistic narrative bias
um and we right and we often because of
introspection
we pay attention to the wrong things
because introspection is a very flawed
uh mechanism very flawed process
so pay much more attention to how people
are reporting to you
um your your transformative trajectory
then your own sense of it
you know have them talk to each other
and so i think if you do that if you pay
attention
to the people that you honor
the people that you think what i mean by
that the people that
you feel are deserving of respect uh
because they have given you good reason
to believe
in their character believe in their
character
and their wisdom and their
care for you and then listen to them
a lot while also cultivating as much as
you can
an ecology of practices that reduces
self-deception and
and then that is what will give you
what is needed to counteract the
tremendous
bias like the narrative bias like
narcissism
like my side bias like confirmation bias
like depressive bias like ruminative
bias that will inevitably creep
into our narratives so i hope that
answers your question um last uh
question or maybe one or two more any
update on the cognitive continuum book
yes uh this is from abcdef
um and the the fault is mine uh
daniel has been working hard and he has
sent me an updated manuscript with
what has happened uh i was supposed to
read it
last uh weekend but i had to
deal with other issues that were more
exigent and so i didn't get to it
hopefully i'll get to it this weekend um
it's still progressing
i'm hoping we'll get it out or at least
get it completed
uh towards the end of this year at the
beginning of next year
i'm also working on two other books at
the same time
i'm working on the anthology which is
going to be in submission to the
publisher within two weeks
uh on dialectic into the logos an
anthology of many of people from this
corner of the internet
the anthology i'm working with it
co-editing it uh
uh uh and co-writing some of the
chapters uh with christopher master
pietro we have people in there
um like craig enriquez like uh guy
sandstock
uh like paul vander clay uh
uh just a whole i'm sorry i i feel like
i'm at the oscars
there's a whole bunch of people in there
uh just amazing uh thomas and elizabeth
uh from uh evolving europe
uh johannes niedermeyer and his amazing
work
on heidegger and his relations to
dialogue anyways
that anthology is is we've been working
very hard on that that's coming to
fruition
uh almost finished also within two or
three weeks
the transcription of the first half
awakening from the meeting crisis the
first 25 episodes are done
we're just finishing up some of the
editing uh there's an extensive
uh glossary uh there uh filling out the
references
uh uh uh madeleine has been amazing work
at that and we're also she's added in
all kinds of figure
so those three three books because we're
doing all three
uh there's a there's a sort of delay
there but we're coming towards
completion
so i'm gonna uh
one last one last question uh enemy of
elder
who's also a patron uh thank you for
your work
greetings john thank you for all of your
monumental and life-changing work
on the meeting crisis and once again i'm
finding deep appreciation for the
grammar that you have
so consistently and beautifully conveyed
throughout that is very much helping me
navigate the world
the series has widened for me now for my
question i think you would have a great
conversation
with sam harris what do you think
i would like to have a conversation with
sam harris um
i've been critical of sam harris at
points within the meeting crisis
sometimes perhaps a little bit harsh
because i find
at times his stance is very strident um
and maybe i over compensated
and sometimes also in voices with raviki
i'm i'm generally critical of the new
atheists because i simultaneously
as many of you know criticized both
atheism and theism i'm a non-theist
and i think both theists and atheists
have a huge
shared set of presuppositions that i
think should be seriously questioned
uh i'm also working on a video series uh
for that which will come out after
after after socrates comes out that
video series on non-theism is called the
god beyond god
and the reinvention of the sacred and
but there's a lot of discussions with
people like
chris the formative piece oh and andrew
sweeney where you can see that
at work and some of the discussions i've
had with paul and jonathan
paul vander clay jonathan pedro um
and so um i'm also
somewhat hesitant
this is not a criticism that i've made
just me other people have noted uh
people who have
have at one time been quite staunch
supporters of sam harris
that he doesn't seem
to be that willing to engage in
self-correction
um and i find that
uh a worrying feature of somebody who is
representing rationality representing
transformation especially
things like mindfulness um
i think we should exemplify to people i
just tried to do it throughout this q a
um our own processes of dealing with
self-deception
admitting when we are wrong uh admitting
when we need to reformulate or even
reconsider
a particular position or theory because
without that capacity
for self-correction we can't
enter into the possibility of mutual
self-correction
of the mutual self-correction that's at
the core
of genuine deal logos
but perhaps i'm wrong and again this is
not false modesty
perhaps if
we were in dialogue and i
i got to talk to sam about my concerns
maybe he would be responsive and
responsible to them and perhaps a
genuine uh
dialogue dear logos as possible i'm
concerned about
how that didn't happen between him and
jordan peterson
uh um i have significant disagreements
with jordan peterson
i have significant agreements with
jordan peterson both
um and i was able to well jordan and i i
don't want to take sole credit
we're able and to enter into a really
good
dialogue that i think towards the end
it's on youtube you can watch it
became genuine deal logos i'm very happy
uh
that jordan peterson is back and i'm i i
would be most happy
jordan if somehow this gets to you um i
would be happy
to enter into another such public
dialogue with you um and so in the
spirit of that
um i would like to avoid what happened
between
sam and jordan and if it was possible
that we could
mutually move towards avoiding that then
i would be happy to talk
to sam harris so i want to thank you all
for joining me on this q q a excellent
questions
uh always nourishing and nurturing
uh from you to me and i hope i'm
restrict recreating back to you
we're doing this every third friday of
the month we should be back on schedule
for november
november typically is a more stable
month
uh because uh in november canada turns
to
just living in the bottom of a
dishwasher it's raining all the time
things are
dark um they're messy and you feel
terrifically closed in
but at least it's stable and stability
helps my ear
thank you for all the supporters over
patreon
please consider if you're not doing it
right now supporting my work on the
meeting crisis
at patreon.com john raviki
and i want to especially thank my dear
friend
and techno mage uh amar who is again
behind the scenes
working his magic making sure that
everything flows smoothly to you
thank you very much everybody and take
good care